[Music]
the stoa
is a digital campfire where we cohere in
dialogue
about what matters most at the knife's
edge of what's happening now
[Music]
welcome everybody uh welcome to the
store
still is a place where we cohere and
dialogue about what matters most at the
knife's edge of this moment
and today we have a session
for communitas club where
we are welcoming jill de temple from
southern methodist university where she
is
a professor of religious studies and i
think chair of the department as well
to talk about a tool called reflective
structure dialogues
so before i hand things off to jill just
to give everyone an
overview of what to expect for this
session um
we're going to have a short presentation
hear about the tool uh some
opportunities for audience participation
and then we'll move into a q a portion
and take it from there so this
is being recorded so
if you don't want to ask your questions
please when you write them in the chat
just
indicate that and i will ask them for
you
and feel free to add questions as they
come up
and we'll uh
throw them out there when we get to it
um
so yeah chill please take it away
well hi i'm so delighted to be here and
be with all of you
thanks to peter and margaret for
bringing me here today
and to all of you again for coming this
is the most amazing thing
that we're able to do this way um what
i'd like to do today is talk about how
i've been using dialogue in classrooms
and specifically using dialogue in
classrooms to encourage engagement
belonging
and then some ethical reasoning with my
students
um i have an exercise i'll have you try
so to get you sort of oriented to what
this stuff is
um and get so you can have a feel for
how this might work
um so it'll be sort of a down and dirty
crash course
in what all of this is um i think it'll
take about 25 minutes to sort of get
through the crash course
and then i'd love to open this up for
some conversation about what's going on
so please though at any time um if
something is really
unclear or especially if you can't hear
me or
you just think i'm going too fast stop
me
ask a question because i get really
excited about this stuff
and i can start talking really really
really quickly
and that's especially hard over zoom so
with that i'm going to do that thing we
do
and share a screen
give me one second to get this where it
will go
there we go so this is
constructive listening uh dialogic
classrooms for engagement belonging and
ethical reasoning
um this comes from
quite a bit of work that's been
happening over several years and so what
i'd like to do is start with the
background of this work
and talk about the basis of it which is
reflective structured dialogue
so what this is um it's a particular
form of dialogic practice developed in
the late 1980s in boston
um and it was developed amongst
practitioners in family therapy to
intervene in really bad family dynamics
but it came into the public sphere right
so out of the office so to speak
in response to a series of abortion
clinic shootings that happened in 1989
uh roughly what happens as the nonprofit
that owns this they are called essential
partners
their practitioners were watching some
truly bad discourse
around those shootings on both sides the
pro-life side and the pro-choice side
and they were starting to understand
that the dynamics they were seeing
looked like those bad family dynamics in
which they were commonly intervening in
their practice
and so they invited um pro-choice and
pro-life folks to a series of actually
secret conversations these happened
in a manner so that nobody was risking
their kind of professional
reputations on them with an idea not
that they would ever
agree about abortion but they could
learn how to re-humanize each other and
have a conversation again
even around those really contentious
issues and long story short is that
actually went really well
um again nobody agreed at the end of the
day
that abortion was either something we
should or shouldn't have in the united
states
but they came away from those
conversations
talking about their ability to
rehumanize that other side a lot of
people became friends after those
conversations
and so that initial group of therapists
decided to found a non-profit at that
time called the public conversations
project
to take this method out onto the streets
and here's what the method is it's
called reflective structure dialogue
and it does indeed privilege reflection
as a practice right this is one thing
that makes a little bit different than
some other forms of dialogue that are
out there you may have run into
um it gives people time to reflect
before
asking them to answer a question or
offer some new idea
or revelation um so one thing i have
learned to do in classrooms for example
is just ask people to take a minute and
think about
before i then go back to my students and
ask them to answer the question
it's like this pedagogical deep breath
and we've engaged reflection um before
we have people speaking before we have
them listening
um i now engage it just to start a class
and kind of make it a ritual in the work
um so that's a really important piece of
this
um one thing i actually want to back up
and realize i didn't say is i
got hooked up with these good folks um
at essential partners
through their current co-executive
director john ceruth
who was a college friend of mine we've
known each other for a really long time
he came into dallas um in 2014 and we
hadn't seen each other in forever
and just went out to have a drink and
the more he was talking about using
these methods it'll
give you this overview of here in just a
minute the more i
understood that would be really useful
um
especially for my graduate students i
teach
folks to go out and teach religion in
public universities
and in private universities and in other
places
what i hadn't been teaching students was
how to have the difficult conversations
around religion
that invariably come up in our
classrooms
i am not so sure i don't know where all
of you are coming from but at least in
the united states and especially in the
southern united states
we have students who were actually told
never to speak about religion or
politics because it would be impolite
and so when we bring them into a
religious studies classroom for the
first time
they really don't know how to have that
intellectual conversation about what
we're trying to talk about
they have no notion about where to start
and we weren't doing ourselves a favor
by not
training our phd students into that sort
of discourse about how to have the
conversation
so i got really interested in what he
was saying and he got really interested
in what i was saying about teaching on a
university campus
because he was getting called more and
more often into
a sort of bias incident problems and
public conversations
does our essential partners now does a
lot of
conflict mediation work a lot of
conflict transformation work
and they've been increasingly called
onto college campuses
and so he wanted to know more about the
culture of those campuses
and the more we started talking and
continuing to talk about things like
free speech issues the more we realized
we really wanted to develop something
and also john was in conversation with
other folks on other campuses so he
brought us all together
and what you'll hear when i get to
dialogic classrooms as a result of all
of those conversations and a lot of
research that we've done
but back to reflective structure
dialogue um again really privileges
taking that breath
for reflection then we use structure to
hold the conversation
most rooms you're in after you've been
there about five minutes you kind of
know who's going to talk and who's not
going to talk it's certainly true in
classrooms
we even know where those people are
going to sit in the room they're
probably our first row off to my left
and it's those five people uh even if i
have a class of 35 or 40.
and that holds up certain structures but
it doesn't allow our quieter people or
the people who may
need a little more time to process a lot
of room to speak or contribute in the
room
and so when we do a full-on reflective
structure dialogue not only do we give
that time for reflection
we put a timer on people i will give you
let's say 90 seconds to think and then
everyone will have 90 seconds to speak
before the days of covid we would pass
the timer around a circle
um now we create that circle on zoom and
the facilitator holds the timer
just using your phone and that structure
and
we ask a specific question to which
people are to respond
that structure allows people to first of
all
speak to what's true to them they've had
time to reflect on it
it also allows them to really listen to
other people
when you've had that time to think about
what you're gonna say and when you know
that you will have your 90 seconds or
two minutes
you can just sort of stop worrying about
your own performance
put that aside for a minute and actually
really engage and listen to what
somebody else has to say
a lot of my students that's been the
revolutionary part of this they realize
they're really listening in a classroom
for the first time ever
especially if they're more nervous about
speaking
for my students who speak a lot it may
be the first time that they have
literally ever
turned around in the classroom and
listened to their classmates
i have one particularly gifted student
who just graduated
who talks about that first time he
turned around
to listen to everybody else in the room
and how powerful that was for him
because he realized he hadn't been doing
it
he was one of those guys in the front
row always talking
then finally we spend a lot of time in
dialogic classrooms
emphasizing listening to understand and
speaking to be understood
so this is not the usual academic mode
of persuasion
when i want students to write a paper
for me with a thesis and use evidence
that's a persuasive piece of writing and
i still want them to do that
but in the classroom especially if we
are just beginning to enter into
territory that may be
divisive i don't want you to persuade
other people
i want you to speak in such a way that
other people could understand where
you're coming from
usually based on a personal experience
or deeply held belief or value
and then i want you to listen not to
hear the holes in somebody else's
argument
but to really understand what it is
they're trying to say to you
so we practice this in a lot of
different ways
so that people are set up to listen to
understand and then speak to be
understood
right because again this is not our
current public discourse it's pretty
different
um and we need to actually give people
some
work at doing all of this the listening
especially
one thing we've come to understand is
that most of our academic curriculum we
give students real credit for speaking
and for writing
both of those things are literally
tagged for instance in my curriculum
here at southern methodist university
we never teach them how to listen it's
not the sort of trophy you get
in your curriculum or you probably never
got a listening award
i'm in high school where you as you may
have gotten a writing or speaking award
and so we're learning we really have to
emphasize the listening part
if we're going to move people into this
space that we're trying to create
so the result of that my meeting up with
this friend and us doing some research
and talking a lot with a lot of other
really talented people
is indeed something we've come to call
dialogic classrooms
what we're trying to do in those
classrooms is inculcate a culture of
curiosity
to use those skills i was just talking
about
so that students will turn to other
students and say so what do you think
about that i knew this was really
working
when indeed i realized i had a class a
few years ago on social science
where students started speaking in that
sort of 90-second snippet they started
doing it very naturally
and then they would just turn around to
their classmates and say so what do you
think about that
i got to pull back they were genuinely
curious and they were having amazing
and intellectual conversations that were
at a completely different level than
anything i'd had before
so this is something we've learned we
really want to emphasize and we talk a
lot about
why curiosity is good for you why it's
going to make you a better student
why it can help you even outside of
school one thing we've noticed when we
use dialogue in classrooms
um so we do full on reflective
structured dialogue and then we have
things we call dialogic moments
and those may be where we just ask
people to reflect on something
is that students told us in follow-up
surveys they had a much
greater sense of belonging in those
classes
they didn't feel alienated they wanted
to come they felt like they had friends
um and perhaps the thing that really
struck us was they felt like whatever
they had to say would be listened to
and they were linking that directly to
the sense that this is a place where
they could be themselves
um i had another place that brought me
to thinking this was a really great idea
is when i had a student reflect
in a piece of writing that she had never
told anyone before on campus what
religion she was
because she felt like it would not be
okay that something about this class
let her share that in a way that she
felt like she would be
supported in some way it's not that
everybody else is going to convert to
her religion but it was that she could
say what was true for her and nobody was
just going to shoot her down
based on some stereotype they had about
her
instead they were going to ask her more
about why she was or where she'd come
from or what her family was like
um the other thing and this is sort of a
happy thing for us
and students we're reporting very high
levels of engagement
in classes where we're using dialogue a
lot um both with other
people in the class with students but
also with course content
and i think the day i may have been
fully converted to doing this really
intentionally all the time
from being sort of casual about it was
when a group of sorority women walked
into my class
in april talking about a
chapter dinner they just had these sort
of meetings they have on mondays
where they were talking about analytic
philosophy with their sorority sisters
you just read some alvin plantinga and i
don't know how many of you do analytic
philosophy but he's a hardcore analytic
philosopher it's a lot like reading math
and they had brought it to their
sorority sisters and were very excited
about this thing and wanted to share it
with people
prior to that moment i was pretty sure
that most of my students in late april
weren't reading anything
much less making their way through a
pretty difficult analytic philosophy
article
so that level of engagement is part of
the piece of the magic
of this for me um as an instructor and
then they were also coming back to share
it and tell me it
happened they were downright excited
that they'd gotten their sorority
sisters
into a down and dirty conversation about
i think it was the problem with evil or
something
with alvin plantinga story so it just
gets students really involved and
excited
in a way that's native to them and it
means they're going to learn stuff
better
it also means they just keep coming to
class
uh the other thing that dialogic
classrooms do
is give students a sense of resilience
students report
that they feel like they can listen to
something with which they deeply
disagree
um and actually listen all the way
through and not just tune it out or shut
down
so there is that connection that can
come
when you feel like you don't have to run
away from something that's difficult
we have a lot of student writing about
that feeling when they realized that
they
were brave enough and the space was
brave enough
that they could hear something that was
really hard because it went up against
a deeply behind deeply held believer
world view
which is really the root of this work
was getting people to that space
and the fact that it gets replicated in
classrooms is fantastic for us
because again it leads to that increased
sense of belonging that culture of
curiosity and that engagement
this is also though what's really
important about this it's this isn't
just for contentious issues
i will use dialogue now to teach about
things like
the idea of design um when i teach
philosophy of religion
we read the analogical teleological
argument for the existence of god which
is a fancy way of saying
you can infer god's existence because of
things like eyes
that there's something in the design of
those that should lead one to and for a
creator
i was having a heck of a time in
previous iterations of that course
getting students to really dig into this
question of design and purpose do we
really know what the purpose is for
something
and so a couple of years ago i just
started with this moment and i asked you
know can you think of a time
when you didn't know what something was
for and then you re then you had this
aha moment and you understood it
and one student talked about a cigarette
lighter in a car
he had this moment where he realized
that one could actually light a
cigarette with it and it wasn't just for
plugging in
electronics and he felt sort of silly
that he'd never understood it but he
also had this
he's like i went through my whole life
not understanding that that thing could
light a cigarette
and another student talked about she'd
bought in a keurig coffee maker
and it came with this little empty mesh
basket and the moment about five weeks
after she'd gotten the coffee maker
where she realized you could put coffee
in the little empty mesh thing and you
wouldn't have to go buy k-cups for they
what this did so everybody could sort of
identify with those stories in the room
and then when we talked about that
analogy leologic argument they realized
because of those stories
that purpose and design are not always
obviously related
and they had a much smarter take about
that particular
philosophy of religion that day it
didn't take me trying to walk them
through it step by step they could just
make the leap and we could get much
deeper into it
so i find this stuff absolute magic for
teaching
it's you know it's yes it's connecting
them yes they feel free to even offer
those sorts of slightly vulnerable
stories in a room or sometimes very
vulnerable stories
but it's just flat out really great for
people learning stuff
so here's where i'd like you to try um
a version of this so what i'll need is
two volunteers
so i'm not sure i can't see everyone
if you'd like to volunteer can you
please indicate it in the chat
donald rush at once i mean margaret and
peter i can pick on you guys too
uh so we have andy okay and
thank you okay andy and to rae so here's
what i'd like you to do andy you're
going to be
person a and this is an exercise we run
students through to get them
to know the difference between asking a
genuine question of curiosity
and a rhetorical question which is not
so curious
and again it's getting them to
understand what we mean when we say
speaking to be understood listening to
understand so
here's how this exercise works andy
you're going to make a statement and it
should be about something you care about
but not necessarily something that is
life and death so maybe
cat videos are the best thing on the
internet
or maybe universal health care is an
absolute human right
pick something that matters to you and
then tarray you're going to spend a
minute and i will keep a timer on you
responding to that question with
questions but they're designed to
persuade
andy out of his stance
all right so if andy says cat videos are
the best thing on the internet you might
come back with how could you possibly
believe that we all know chameleon
internet
video is the best thing on the internet
and you're going to keep going back and
forth
right for one minute and then i'm going
to have you do something else
so you guys ready
so if youtube went on mute yep and andy
go ahead and make your statement
education is a human right
quality education
um
do you believe that everyone should
really be educated
what do you mean by education or
educated in your
thought
[Laughter]
um maybe some people
aren't um able to be educated in the way
that we want them to so should we
[Music]
waste our time and efforts and educating
everyone with the same quality
well they have to be interested in
something i would imagine that they have
a
enthusiasm or passion for maybe we can
find that
and then educate toward that passion
okay your minute is up
now i want you to switch not switch
roles but andy i want you to make that
same statement
and to ray what you're going to do
is ask questions designed to understand
andy's perspective his thinking
his feelings maybe why he thinks that so
you might ask it sounds like education
is important to you why is that
right so let's try that for a minute
andy go ahead and make your statement
i think quality education is a universal
right
um sounds like this is an important
topic for you
why do you think it's a universal right
we all need a set of tools
to better
further ourselves and improve our
well-being rather than just
finding it individually by ourselves
what would it look like if everyone had
a quality education
[Music]
wow that's a great question um
i think there's a way that we have to
adjust for people's different ways of
learning and how they learn and
understanding that first
and then finding out what it is they get
excited about
and then trying to teach toward that
okay i'm gonna stop you there so andy
what was
it like being asked those rhetorical
questions oh
man it um it really makes you
think more deeply about your stated
belief
and have not only a plan but
but some kind of
i don't know deeper
um
explanation of why how
how did you come to this yeah yes
yes it sounds like you're actually
talking about that second those curious
questions
all right because she came back yeah
yeah what would that actually look like
for you
yeah and that's this that's what this
exercise is designed to do to rae what
was it like
what was the difference for you between
that first round and that second round
uh it was um
[Music]
it's easier for me to ask questions from
a place of curiosity
to understand things so when i had to
role play the first scenario it was
a little bit more challenging to have
this underlying motive
to discredit yeah the statement
that challenged my thinking
well yeah a lot of people get really
anxious when they have to go into that
rhetorical persuasive
mode right yeah so this is the kind of
work we do with students
to really show them the difference
between what it's like
to sort of ask a question to attack and
what it's like to ask that more curious
question
and most of our students would come away
with a very similar response with like
wow i learned a lot more about my own
convictions around that issue for
example
when you actually asked me you know what
would that look like
uh and they also report not being as
anxious or
and they report listening to each other
much better
so thank you guys um i'm gonna take
another just couple minutes to finish up
with the
talking about what these classrooms look
like uh and then open it up to some
questions
um this is based on some research we got
a large grant to
look at what happens when we train
faculty into dialogic classrooms and
then we surveyed their students
um and so when we asked um
them to rate so the opportunity to
dialogue in this classroom helped me
feel a sense of belonging in the class
what you see
is this overwhelming agreement that it
did
it was so overwhelming actually we went
back to retool the question we thought
we'd completely blown it because it
didn't seem statistically possible to us
uh but this range was absolutely
verified each and every time we did it
um overwhelmingly
like 90 of students talked about
belonging in dialogic classrooms and
having that sense
increase because they've been able to
talk to other
classmates in the way the dialogue
encourages
this is the course content um question
please specify the degree to which
dialogues held during class helped you
better understand the course content
readings
and again you'll see it's really heavily
skewed towards people telling us
that not only was dialogue good for
their sense of belonging um
but they felt like they just understood
what was going on in the course much
better
and there's something about i think it's
their engagement and we need to do more
research to understand why this is true
but again if we've got sorority women
bringing up analytic philosophy
at chapters and i think it's because
they were reading more
and talking about it more and just
feeling like it belonged to them in a
way that
maybe normally isn't the case
um and here's the other thing we got
excited about students were much more
willing to speak
in these classes uh faculty had reported
that the
number of students speaking in a room
was much higher than usual
and students reported they were much
more willing to speak
the other thing that was really happy
for us is this willingness to speak did
not
correlate with their idea that people
would agree with what they had to say
there was no statistical correlation
there
so they were wanting to speak more um
and actually the students who
on this particular histogram had said
they wanted to speak less when we went
back in to fine-tune that question
they were speaking less because they
wanted to listen more it's not because
they felt like the atmosphere was
somehow not conducive to speaking
so just to wrap up this is a
picture that some faculty drew for us
about the classroom from hell what they
don't want
it's got silent students in the back
they're distracted
um some constant talker in the front you
can't move furniture
they're sort of in that awful setup that
we have you know the stadium seating the
room is dark
um and so one question we've been
dealing with and wanting to dig into
more is how do we create this culture of
engagement
and then how can we move that outside of
classrooms into civic or ethical region
how do we go from that awful diagram to
something more like this
where students are fully engaged with
each other
in a way that they could take you know
outside of this particular controlled
atmosphere of a classroom
um to get at that um
we create these conditions and one
reason that those classrooms work
is we have communication agreements that
students themselves create
we ask students in this exercise we call
moment of descent um
what would it take for you to say
something different after seven people
have all just said the same thing or
supported the same view in a classroom
but what is true for you is not true for
them based on a deeply held value or
belief
and this is an example of what students
will put up on a board and from which we
craft the agreements
what this does is allow me to enforce
those agreements in a class
right so if our agreement is to be open
to minority opinion
right or to let people develop and
conclude comments before responding so
not interrupting
if somebody in a class interrupts i can
say i'm going to pause you there we have
this agreement that you're not going to
interrupt
right so we'll get to you we all are
going to have time but please
stop interrupting for now
um that is the kind of thing we're
hoping students will move out and
they're starting to report
that they're moving out to the bigger
world
um one way i'm having students think
about that bigger world is with this
question
how do you want to be in the world and
this is developed with a university
ethics professor steve long here at
southern methodist university
for him this is sort of the basis of
ethics
and i just wanted to share a couple of
answers that my students have given to
this question
when posed to them i want to be someone
who understands all sides of a problem
before deciding what i think and someone
who is always open to new
interpretations
this class helped me see a new way of
doing that through non-combative
discussion
[Applause]
i don't want to be known as someone who
doesn't listen to the other side of an
argument because this doesn't get
anything done
this class taught me the value of
listening actually listening
to try and understand where other people
are coming from
and then this one one of my absolute
favorites um
i have not by any means become an eager
political reformist who goes out to
peddle their beliefs on the street
corner
but this class did teach me that
dialogue between people that don't agree
is possible
and it can be civil understanding and
productive
i used to joke that i was a passive
anarchist waiting for civilization to
crumble under the weight of twitter and
all of its friends
however our dialogues and the outlook of
the class gave me hope for a world where
i can listen and be heard by people who
don't have the exact same political
beliefs as me
after all we can't get anything done if
we're not listening to each other
she then went on actually to name the us
congress as an example of people not
listening
so that is the hope and that is the
basic approach to this thing
and i welcome your questions and
comments
great thank you jill um
yeah i'm i'm really struck by
the idea that when we feel we are being
listened to
we are much more careful about what we
say um i'm
we're much more thoughtful i should say
about what we put out in our speech
uh so we have a couple of questions that
came up
um andy would you like to unmute and
start with yours
and then sure so at the beginning you
were talking about these uh
time-based um sessions where
one person goes then you kind of go
around the circle and
um then uh in
the exercise we did it was more
kind of improvisational and so how do
you incorporate
um both so that both the quiet people
can be heard and you um
can't allow for follow-up questions and
um great question
yeah so the general structure of those
really formal dialogues i mean you
actually kind of got a feel for that i
think you were on timers
right even in the improvisation there
um so that's a way that structure can
actually support that kind of back and
forth
but the generals there's a general
structure to most of those formal
dialogues and the first question
the first go-round um asked people to
tell a story
that would help us understand how they
came to believe what they believe
about guns in american society abortion
whatever the thing is so everybody will
speak one at a time about that
and then the second question generally
digs a little bit deeper
into what is the heart of the matter for
you what values
are you drawing on as you think about
what you believe about whatever the
thing is
and then a third question we'll ask
where you feel pulled
in different directions right most
people even if they're sort of
hard on one side of an issue do have
some reservations
right so if you're a hardcore second
amendment person here in the united
states
for gun ownership um you know they may
still feel like not everybody should
have a gun and they may have some
reservations and that allows them to
express that complexity for them
and then there's a fourth round where we
have
encouraged people throughout the
dialogue to write down their curious
questions for one another
and that's when we give them about 20
minutes of back and forth of those
curious questions
right um so i did a gun dialogue um
in a class here in texas something i
never ever thought i would want to do
i went with fear and trepidation into
this thing um
and somebody in his first round was
talking about growing up in a very small
town
there was no movie theater and they
entertained themselves by running around
his backyard with rifles
and so a student who is not she's from
an urban setting
it you know this entire time she's dying
to ask the question she finally got to
ask
in that open round which is how big is
your backyard
she couldn't picture acreage right she
comes she came from urban california
with a pretty small you know
and they came to understood stand they
understood guns
really differently she was thinking of
sort of gang violence stuff
which he couldn't really imagine right
and he was imagining shooting feral hogs
because that's actually where you need a
pretty big weapon here in texas
and they had this aha moment where
without those stories
they would have just said sort of i'm
pro-second amendment i am pro-gun
control and they never would have
understood that they're not even really
talking in some ways about the same
thing
it was just amazing to sort of watch
them
unfold and have these moments like that
so that's where that
that back and forth happens that it's
after you've heard somebody's story
their values and the complexity of that
story
because that sets you up to ask the
really great curious questions that are
going to move you along
yeah great great question
did you have a follow-up andy
okay evan would you like to ask your
question
sure thanks so um i really love this
methodology for running a classroom
style discussion uh but it seems to me
that it
heavily relies on the top-down control
structure of the teacher who has
institutional authority determining the
ground rules for interaction in the
classroom
so i'm curious about your thoughts as to
how we can use this sort of thing
and the kind of wild west of modern
political and social discourse
specifically because the ground rules of
debate are often themselves points of
extreme contention so for example we
look at the debate playing out in the
news right now regarding the
presidential debate structure where
muting
candidates during the other candidates
specifically allotted time
is highly contentious and being resisted
by one of the campaigns so just curious
know your thoughts on that because i
love the methodology
yeah so that's where something we talk a
lot about is preparation
if people aren't going to buy into those
basic ground rules this would be almost
impossible to use
i do think the killer curious question
is really useful that's something i take
out even if we haven't had this
discussion
about how what rules we're going to
operate by even if we don't have a
facilitator
um a couple of you guys when i first
came in i've got this little ninja
figure
um that is my zoom icon that came from a
group of faculty who talked about being
a dialogue ninja in faculty meetings
which can be truly terrible
where they would even if they don't have
the authority in the room
they've started using some of these
techniques to say
um you know i don't think you're in you
know you didn't mean for that to sound
that way
right and i don't think your intentions
were bad but it really landed that way
on me do you think you could say that a
different way
and they just kind of back it up before
it explodes in the room
because that's another thing we talk a
lot about in the work is the difference
between intention and impact
and if those things aren't aligned
that's when things can go badly really
quickly
but back to your debate question i
again the one reason this works in
classrooms is because we co-create those
agreements
and you're right we co-create them
because i make them do it because i have
the authority in the room
that's much more difficult in a much
more lateral situation
um but i do think i found myself sort of
out in the wild
using a lot of these ideas my students
have as well they'll come back and
report
that they've just learned to ask that
curious question about the experience
that leads to the belief
a couple of years ago a student walked
up to me during my office hours and she
i thought she was there for a paper or
something she's like i just wanted to
thank you thanksgiving was so much
better
she had managed to ask yeah she's
polarized from her family and she'd
managed to actually just ask
could you just tell me a story that
would help me understand
like it took everything she had in that
moment to
back it off and ask and turns out there
was something
really deep in the story where they
could relate and
have a more real conversation over
something that was very contentious
and she could remember their
relationship better in the moment
so that's something i think people are
able to do
right and to remember your own good
intentions and that's what i love about
that how do you want to be in the world
question it asks about your intentions
in a conversation
how can you be your best self what are
you going to have to do
and it might be asking about somebody's
intention instead of just feeling that
body below impact
when somebody says something that just
lays you out because it goes against
something that you hold dear
it's hard but we got to start somewhere
helpful yeah thanks i especially like
the focus on the curiosity question that
that's useful thank you
yeah thank you those are like golden for
me
not always easy to come up with in the
moment but
yeah other questions uh yeah um
so jamie had a question about is there a
list of these guiding questions
somewhere
yeah so um essential partners and which
is
www.whatisessential.org i'll put that up
in the chat for you in a second um
they've actually got a red blue guide
which that's us terminology i don't know
how many of you are coming in from where
um about difficult conversations that
has a lot of
these sorts of guides guiding questions
in it
so you can for the i think they ask you
for the price of your email address
but then you're free to use some of
those materials they also have a section
on higher education
um and a few others religious groups i
think is another place that they have
some publicly available materials
so congregations that might be divided
over sexuality or other issues
let me i'll get that up for you guys
jill do you have any other suggestions
of how one
can personally develop their own
practice
of asking more curious questions or
developing their own questions of
understanding
yeah um
i think just the practice of that
reflective moment that taking a breath
um sometimes i'll ask myself did i take
a breath or did i just react
right because your brain is geared to
react one reason this is so
hard if
um you know
your brain can't tell the difference
between a physical threat and a
viewpoint threat so when somebody says
the thing you're responding as if they
literally are trying to hit you
that has been really useful information
for me to have because i can sort of
say okay i'm triggered into fight flight
or freeze
and my that means i don't have access to
my rational brain right now
and it'll probably be about 20 minutes
before i do again
so if i can take a breath and maybe
shift over
and then come back the coming back is
hard
but if i can come back into the space
and say so
then i can come up with that great
curious question
but yeah just knowing your own
limitations about that and but also
knowing your strengths where can you
lean in
right so i'm a teacher i'm pretty good
at coming up with questions in the
moment to move a conversation along
amongst people who probably want to be
taking a nap
all right um i can lean into those
strengths
you know and maybe in the if especially
if it's a group
ask one person that one curious question
that might help us go
you know so if your job is you know my
husband works with spreadsheets all the
time
um you know his job is you know he's
really good at organizing and sorting
stuff out he might be better at taking
more organizational approach to that
kind of thing because that's how his
mind works
um but yeah just a lot of practice until
the question that you would normally
never ask
becomes something that you can
it takes i'm an introvert it takes a lot
of bravery i never
thought i had um
uh that's really useful the question you
never thought you'd ask becomes your
norm
i'm working on it um and but also know
when maybe it's not going to get you
if your intention may be something but
the impact may be different too
sometimes it's your own intention
impact gap you got to be careful about
is this really going to be helpful in
this moment
checking in with the with your
surroundings i think is also
really great or you'll be like changing
lanes and traffic without looking
so again that that breath to reflect on
what is it we're trying to do
what's at stake for me for this
relationship
and then trying to proceed it's not
always easy to do
thank you uh elizabeth did you want to
unmute and ask your question
sure um you know i was curious i have a
teenager
and i'm just wondering um as a
facilitator myself it's been
a challenge to always understand how to
pull the group
in in that sort of pregame capacity to
actually do this work together or any
work frankly
and i was just wondering how you might
help gather your students
to ground them to get them ready to be
present because i do think especially
for gen
z's and i really don't want to pick on a
generation but i live with one of
those members i know how many
distractions and how
uh how tempting it is to uh
be absorbed in other things that do not
require the same
type of human groundedness to
to you know interact with and to relate
to humans all the time
yeah now that's a great question thank
you
so another principle of the work that
you'll hear a lot if you hang out with
essential partners people
is connection before content people
before process
and it's something i have taken to heart
i connect my classes now before we start
anything
and right now it's super challenging
because i've got about
14 of them on zoom and four in a
physical classroom and we're trying to
bridge the zoom room
gap um amongst all the other gaps we're
normally trying to bridge
so one thing i found really effective
and we did this i was just teaching at a
high school about this stuff and it
worked for that age group as well
is to just do a connected moment
um so for the high school because we
were virtual we just we put them into
smaller zoom room breakout rooms
and asked a connective question um so it
was what band or artists get to you
right talk about that and we had them
model the weather forecast for their
mood they were in that day
something you're recently in love with
is a great question
one good thing about today is another
one that i really like
my students here on campus just did some
beautiful things with that one
today we did one thing you said hello to
um
maybe one thing you're worried about so
those
questions that allow people to share
something that's not too
i mean one thing you'll notice in those
agreements is we can pass or pass for
now
i need to give people agency over what
they say in a room where they're not
with their best friends
they're you know with people they may
even be opposed to on campus
so it has to be something you could
answer in any number of ways and you
choose the depth
to which you're going to go into which
you will share
but i am i will now take about three or
four minutes the beginning of every
class to make sure we just have that
moment so we can be in a space together
and as a teacher it's fabulous because i
can get a read on the room
um the other thing i did for this
semester is give people emojis
and because i can't see them behind the
masks and then
i was doing emoji check-ins how are you
feeling and the day that they all held
up the anxiety emoji i knew we needed to
take a minute and
talk about what was in the room super
helpful because
it's going to be in the room no matter
what it's better if you know that it's
there
and you know getting back to teenagers
they want that they really like that
they like being listened to that way
and interacting with peers that way i
find that to be a pretty
native motivation for them they think
it's fun
um i'm not sure my kids would think it's
fun if i went home and asked them to do
it
but it's fun if somebody they're not
related to and in a bigger social group
ask them to do it
uh toure invitation to ask you a
question
thanks um i was just wondering how you
can explore
with curiosity if someone feels like
either
you have it ulterior motives or just
like generally
isn't comfortable with being vulnerable
and
you sort of touched on this in the last
statement that you made around like
establishing the connection before the
content
um but i'm wondering if you have more
on how for people that have a lot of
armoring yeah uh what
what how how do we switch how can we
help engage them into like switching
into that curiosity
and let them know it's like a safe place
yeah i think well i think the first
thing i would say it's never completely
safe but it has to be a brave
space and a safe enough space yeah and
we do that
through kind of relentless scaffolding
so you don't start with the gun dialogue
the first day
not happening um i talk to students
about
having a dialogic classroom what it
means to be in a dialogic classroom
they i have them do something called the
open mind platform that heterodox
academy puts out
and this is something that gets them
into the language
of being open-minded and curious about
people
and then we do these connective
exercises i have them do that questions
of persuasion and understanding we
create
those agreements for the room and then
we can start having the conversations
and for most students that's enough it
gets them
feeling like they are supported and
they're not going to fall into a black
hole
the other thing about the dialogues is
you always have that option to pass or
pass for now
and you always choose the story you
share
so students will self-regulate rightly
so and some of them
go really pretty deep um
amazingly so and some of them are more
reserved because they never
feel that that's appropriate for them
so this is it helps and
i'm not in a classroom environment and
i'm not
you know in that container and so as i'm
thinking about how to apply this to
everyday life right that that
that environment isn't the everyday
environment and so i'm wondering if
there
is like um
[Music]
a way to create that without having all
you know that prior environment that
comes with education is wonderful but
what about on the streets what about
you know one-on-one and you know a
parking lot i mean how do you yeah
you know those connective questions are
amazing
so i've been doing a lot of this work
where i'll be with like a non-profit
um and i'll just go around the circle
and have you know you say your name
and then one thing you're recently in
love with and i just
watched the barriers sort of go away in
the room
because they realize that two of them
have had coveted gardens or a couple of
them have puppies or
they're able to make that connection at
a human level and that sets up the
conditions under which
we could start having these
conversations yeah um and i
yeah you're right about like the grocery
store um
so i think not just starting with hey
who you voting for
but talk about one good thing that's
happened to you lately what are you
hoping for
hope is a really powerful concept
all right so what are you hoping for
lately
where are your hopes lie i think that's
a way of rolling back from issues and
into the values under the issues that
can
make people able to speak about what's
true for them in a way that isn't so
confrontational
yeah thank you
jeff would you like to ask your question
all right i'll give it a go just gonna
just read it though
uh heavy response surveys measured
retention of content
uh what you showed us was it was an
impressive uh attitude change
and it kind of kind of measures up with
with some experiences i've had
but but of course this is a the time
range is short i don't know how much
people have
been in a while but have you tried so um
what we have is you know professors will
come back and say that students and
we're generally doing better in classes
so we have sort of anecdotal evidence
because that was not measured in our
surveys we can't put it forth as you
know
research stuff but what part of the
research study also we
interviewed professors about what they
were doing in classes and what they
hoped to get
and in the course of those interviews we
had professors talking about students
doing better on
tests and then i can also tell you from
the student responses
they were spelling the name of french
theorists right six weeks later
which is not normal because they had
had that theorist presented to them
along with a dialogue
and so again all the anecdotal evidence
would support the students report that
they're actually learning stuff better
this is research i really want to do
really really really want to do
i'm looking for funding to do a much
more broad scale
study that would actually incorporate
that and then also
how this may be either proportionally or
disproportionately spread across
different identity groups as well
because we didn't really we coded for
gender and class status so like
sophomore
freshman freshman senior but we didn't
dig into things like first generational
status
um or ethnicity in the survey that we
did and we think it's important
and so that's research that we wanted
you going forward
i think i think i've sold that that
it's at least very plausible in the in
the
in the classroom setting where you have
an extended engagement
um but for people who are just
meeting up for for an hour wondering
how we escaped the uh um
you know either agreed to disagree or
just talk about things that no one
could disagree about which is like you
know what your favorite animal is or
something
um so but but i think for the longer
engagement it makes sense if people feel
safe and they're gonna
they're gonna engage uh and they'll have
a lot there'll be a lot there for them
to do
sure
other questions yeah i think um
maybe we'll take one more before we wrap
it up um
sawyer did you want to ask your question
yeah um my question was about
whether you've run into um
students subjects people you're
introducing to this concept
who are particularly resistant to it
and if there's any ways to help them
become more comfortable with it that you
found
yeah and i have students who are
terrified of this both so they're sort
of the two groups of students who i find
have a difficult time engaging initially
are
students who feel like it's sort of a
trojan horse where i'm trying to convert
them into some sort of viewpoint they
don't natively hold
um and they that the discourse around
open-mindedness they're like no i know
what i think
and then students who are on that more
vulnerable side who
really are uncomfortable being asked and
to engage this way
um and that takes some scaffolding
and experience i asked them just to try
it and i point out that they don't have
to share anything they don't they could
pass the entire time that would be fine
um but that maybe they should think
about
um trying to listen to understand um
and a couple of things and that app is
really has been really really helpful
for me because it's not me talking to
them it's the app and it's sort of
gamified and they level up and they
um and it's sort of businessy in its
orientation
so for my students coming from that
business school world
it kind of sells them on open mind and
this is the stance they might at least
want to try
and then for my students on that
reluctant side because they
feel like they want to be more sheltered
than that
and about their own identity their
response has been overwhelmingly
positive once they've done one of the
dialogues and understood what it's about
i'm remembering a particular student who
came up to me after our first one
in a class and just said i was so
skeptical of this i didn't think i'd
want to share
anything i just had this amazing
conversation
this is great for the first time ever i
feel like i'm sharing
things that matter with classmates and
we're not just talking about stuff
um so for her it was a matter of trying
it
um and i i've been amazed that i
really don't have dissenters like it's
students universally are coming back and
saying that this is something they want
to see
other places they're trying to embark on
in other places in their life
and it made the course better for them
no matter who they are
i would say you know if you break up
your campus social groups but it's my
greek students my athletes
my first gen students my immigrant kids
like
they all are finding a way to intersect
with it and it's just making class a lot
more interesting for them frankly
than listening to me talk about
something um
so yeah it's so far just been a matter
of
having them try getting beefed up the
place where they think they can try it
and then they kind of carry it from
there
i facilitate they're trying it and then
they take it forward
thanks
okay uh any closing thoughts or
reflections
jill that you'd like to share yeah this
has been so much fun and these are such
great questions um for those of you
again who are
interested in this we would love to hear
from you or
you know just keep the conversation
going so again if you talk
either send me an email or go to that
essential partners website
there's a lot of stuff that we've made
available there that i think a lot of
you would find useful
um yeah all kinds of stuff from the
research project and then
actual examples of dialogic syllabi and
exercises for courses
and then aside from the higher ed um
piece of it um things like that red blue
conversation guide which are more geared
towards those
coffee table conversations a lot of you
were wondering about
they're really good at this
thank you all great
thank you so much for thank you for
sharing with us
um thank you for taking your time
uh really quickly just to let everyone
here know
about uh an event that's happening at
the stoa this evening
uh we'll have derek sivers here
today at 7 pm eastern to talk about
entrepreneurial entrepreneurialism
it's a difficult word as a spiritual
practice
uh so come check it out if you're so
inclined
and keep an eye out for our next
segment of communitas club thank you
again jill
thanks everybody